<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>/home/adeel - automation</title><link>https://adl1995.github.io/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 21:30:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Creating a JSON logger for Flask</title><link>https://adl1995.github.io/creating-a-json-logger-for-flask.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;By default Flask writes logs to the console in plain-text format. This can be limiting if you intend to store your logs in a text file and periodically send them to a central monitoring service. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/kibana/"&gt;Kibana&lt;/a&gt;, only accepts &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JSON&lt;/span&gt; logs by&amp;nbsp;default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might also want to enrich your logs with additional metadata, e.g. timestamps, method names, log type (Warn, Debug, etc.). In this post we will use the Python &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/logging.html"&gt;logging&lt;/a&gt; library to modify Flask&amp;#8217;s logging format and write them to a text file. In the end we will see how to periodically send these logs to an external service using &lt;a href="https://flume.apache.org/"&gt;Flume&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our app we would like to setup two types of loggers. One for …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Adeel Ahmad</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 21:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:adl1995.github.io,2022-08-09:/creating-a-json-logger-for-flask.html</guid><category>automation</category></item><item><title>Passwordless logins with Yubikey</title><link>https://adl1995.github.io/passwordless-logins-with-yubikey.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Yubikey is currently the de facto device for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U2F&lt;/span&gt; authentication. It enables adding an extra layer of security on top of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSH&lt;/span&gt;, system login, signing &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPG&lt;/span&gt; keys, and so on. It is also compatible with several other authentication methods, such as WebAuthn and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAM&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will show how to leverage your Yubikey for unlocking the system lock-screen, both with and without using a password. It will then delve into how to automatically lock the screen when the Yubikey is&amp;nbsp;unplugged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve logins with Yubikeys we require a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAM&lt;/span&gt; configuration. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PAM&lt;/span&gt; or Pluggable Authentication Modules define the authentication flow for common Linux utilities, such as &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;su&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;passwd&lt;/code&gt;. We will override the default authentication flow for the &lt;a href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/xlock"&gt;xlock …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Adeel Ahmad</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 07:50:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:adl1995.github.io,2020-11-29:/passwordless-logins-with-yubikey.html</guid><category>automation</category></item><item><title>Plotting graphical data using RRDtool and a Python Collectd plugin</title><link>https://adl1995.github.io/plotting-graphical-data-using-rrdtool-and-a-python-collectd-plugin.html</link><description>&lt;!-- Date: 2019-05-30 07:57 --&gt;
&lt;!-- Title: Using RRDtool and a Python Collectd plugin to graph weather data --&gt;
&lt;!-- Title: Plotting graphs data from a Python Collectd plugin using RRDtool --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectd is Unix daemon used for periodically collecting system usage statistics, which can include identifying &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt; or memory bottleneck issues. The collected data can then be transformed to graphs using &lt;a href="https://oss.oetiker.ch/rrdtool"&gt;RRDtool&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grafana"&gt;Grafana&lt;/a&gt; dashboard (Grafana provides real time graphs and complex search&amp;nbsp;queries).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The daemon itself is modular and functions through external plugins with each plugin performing a distinct function. This post will explore a plugin which &lt;em&gt;collects weather information of a given city&lt;/em&gt;. The first section will explain how the plugin configuration works and how to plot a graph of the output data using RRDtool. Finally, we will delve into the plugin internals and see how it is&amp;nbsp;written.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: For an intro on how to setup Collectd …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Adeel Ahmad</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 May 2020 11:02:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:adl1995.github.io,2020-05-11:/plotting-graphical-data-using-rrdtool-and-a-python-collectd-plugin.html</guid><category>automation</category></item><item><title>Programmatically organising your backpacking trip using Google My Maps</title><link>https://adl1995.github.io/programmatically-organising-your-backpacking-trip-using-google-my-maps.html</link><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post has been converted from a &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/10NlBmnUk7qsh0nPso3Lqg8OvoP6CZg8sHJx1gllHem4/edit#slide=id.g577465d654_0_0"&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; I gave during the &lt;a href="https://indico.cern.ch/event/771113/overview"&gt;Thematic &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CERN&lt;/span&gt; School of Computing 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When planning a journey to a new country or a city it helps to mark down all the places you would like to visit and eventually create a travel plan for each day. I personally use Google Maps for finding places of interest including historical buildings, museums, and libraries. As an example, if I was to visit say Split, Croatia I could search for &amp;#8220;places to visit split&amp;#8221; on Google Maps. It will then list all the attractions based on features such as reviews and&amp;nbsp;popularity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://adl1995.github.io/images/google-my-maps/things-to-do-split.png" alt="Things to do in Split" style="width:300px;"/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it is possible to individually &amp;#8220;Save&amp;#8221; each place in Google Maps, it does not …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Adeel Ahmad</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2019 09:14:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:adl1995.github.io,2019-05-30:/programmatically-organising-your-backpacking-trip-using-google-my-maps.html</guid><category>Automation</category></item><item><title>Building RPM packages with rpmbuild, Koji, and GitLab-CI</title><link>https://adl1995.github.io/building-rpm-packages-with-rpmbuild-koji-and-gitlab-ci.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; system facilitates the user to query and update a software package. It also allows examining package interdependencies, and verifying package file permissions. This blog post will describe the process of building an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; package using the &lt;code&gt;rpmbuild&lt;/code&gt; utility and will then explain how to schedule build tasks using Koji. Finally, it will describe how to automate the build pipeline using continuous integration in&amp;nbsp;GitLab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; Package&amp;nbsp;Manager&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; Package Manager is an open-source package management system which was originally designed for Red Hat Linux, but it is now supported on most Linux distributions. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; packages can generally be of two&amp;nbsp;types:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Binary &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt;: A binary &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RPM&lt;/span&gt; contains the compiled binary of a complete application (or a library …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Adeel Ahmad</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 08:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:adl1995.github.io,2019-05-06:/building-rpm-packages-with-rpmbuild-koji-and-gitlab-ci.html</guid><category>Automation</category></item></channel></rss>